John Shirley Wood Papers
John Shirley Wood Papers
1917-1967
Wood, John S. (John Shirley), 1888-1966.
4.5 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Army officer. Collection consists of correspondence (1928-1967); articles and speeches on military subjects (1934-1967); photographs (1937-1965); and memorabilia (1917-1966), including address books. Notable correspondents include Creighton W. Abrams, Hanson Baldwin, Alan Bible, Howard W. Cannon, Bruce C. Clarke, James B. Conant, Bing Crosby, William O. Douglas, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Leopold Figl, J. William Fulbright, Lyndon B. Johnson, Robert F. Kennedy, Curtis E. LeMay, Basil Henry Liddell Hart, John L. McClellan, Frank Pace, George S. Patton, Francis T.P. Plimpton, Syngman Rhee, Eddie Rickenbacker, L. Mendel Rivers, Karl F. Rolvaag, Eleanor Roosevelt, DeWitt C. Smith, Robert A. Taft, Maxwell D. Taylor, James A. Van Fleet, William C. Westmoreland, Stephen M. Young, and others.
148764
Biographical History
Major General John Shirley Wood (1888-1966) was an American army officer and writer on military history and strategy, particularly relating to field artillery.
Born January 11, 1888 at Monticello, Arkansas, John Shirley Wood was the son of Arkansas Supreme Court Justice Carroll D. Wood and Reola (Thompson) Wood. He received his B.S. from the University of Arkansas in 1907 and graduated from West Point Military Academy in 1912. In 1924 he attended the Command and General Staff School, and in 1931 the Ecole de Guerre in Paris. The University of Arkansas awarded him an honorary LL.D. degree in 1946
Much of General Wood's early career was in the academic world. He served at West Point as football coach, instructor in chemistry, and Commandant of Cadets. He was also head of the military departments at Culver Military Academy and the University of Wisconsin.
General Wood commanded various field artillery units including the Division Artillery of the 1st Division and of the 2d Armored Division. His staff duties included service as Executive Officer (XO) of the Hawaiian Field Artillery Brigade, as a division staff officer of the 3rd Division in France (1918), as Chief of Staff of the Third Army (1939-1940), and as Chief of Staff of the 1st Armored Corps (1941). As a general officer he held a combat command of the 5th Armored Division. From 1942 to 1944 he commanded the 4th Armored Division, leading it in the advance from Normandy across France into Germany. From 1945 until his retirement from the Army in 1946, he was in command of the Replacement Training Center at Fort Knox, Kentucky.
For his service in combat, General Wood received the Distinguished Service Cross, the Distinguished Service Medal, the Silver Star, the Bronze Star, and the Air Medal. He was also awarded the Croix de Guerre with palm, and the Rosette of the Legion d'honneur for his service in France.
After his retirement from the Army, General Wood served as Chief of Mission for the International Refugee Organization in Austria (1947-1952), Chief of Mission for the United Nations Reconstruction Administration in Tokyo, Korea, and Geneva (1952-1953), and Civil Defense Director for Reno, Nevada (1957-1958).
During the years prior to World War II, General Wood's reviews and digests of French, German, Italian, and Spanish military literature appeared in a number of military journals.
General Wood died on July 2, 1966 in Reno, Nevada, and is buried at West Point Cemetery in West Point, New York. He was married to Abigail Harvey Wood, with whom he had a son, Colonel John S. Wood, and a daughter Shirley.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Shirley Wood Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and memorabilia.
Correspondence is primarily with friends and members of Congress; it concerns both personal affairs and national and international matters such as the Vietnam War, retirement pay for officers, nuclear weapons policy, military strategy and army recruitment and training.
Writings include articles, an autobiographical piece, a column, a foreword, memoranda, notes and outlines, obituaries for friends and for himself, speeches, and a transcript of a telephone conversation. Documents are in several forms, including manuscript, typescript, mimeograph, and printed.
Photographs in the collection are of General Wood, his friends, and places he served tours of duty. There are also two photograph albums.
Memorabilia include personal items such as address books, awards, citations, commissions, degrees, date books, bills and receipts, maps, obituaries and memorials, newspaper clippings about Wood, and printed material on subjects of interest to him.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged either alphabetically (incoming) or chronologically (outgoing). Writings are subdivided into those about Wood and those by Wood; within that, they are alphabetized by type of material. Photographs and memorabilia are arranged in roughly alphabetical order.
Related Material
See also the
Hanson W. Baldwin Papers
, which relate entirely to Baldwin's unpublished biography of General Wood.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Abrams, Creighton W. (Creighton Williams), 1914-1974.; Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991.; Bible, Alan, 1909-1988.; Cannon, Howard W.; Clarke, Bruce C. (Bruce Cooper), 1901-1988.; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978.; Crosby, Bing, 1903-1977.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Figl, Leopold, 1902-1965.; Fulbright, J. William (James William), 1905-1995.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; LeMay, Curtis E.; Liddell Hart, Basil Henry, Sir, 1895-1970.; McClellan, John L. (John Little), 1896-1977.; Pace, Frank, Jr., 1912-1988.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1923-; Plimpton, Francis T. P. (Francis Taylor Pearsons), 1900-1983.; Rhee, Syngman, 1875-1965.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973.; Rivers, L. Mendel (Lucius Mendel), 1905-1970.; Rolvaag, Karl F., 1913-1990.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Smith, DeWitt C. (DeWitt Clinton), 1920-; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Taylor, Maxwell D. (Maxwell Davenport), 1901-1987.; Van Fleet, James A. (James Alward), 1892-1992.; Westmoreland, William C. (William Childs), 1914-2005.; Wood, John S. (John Shirley), 1888-1966.; Young, Stephen M. (Stephen Marvin), 1889-1984.; United States. -- Army.; United States. -- Army -- Officers.; United States -- History, Military -- 20th century.; Address books.; Articles.; Sound recordings.; Audiotapes.; Correspondence.; Phonograph records.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. John S. Wood, 1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Abrams, Maj. Gen. Creighton, 1945-1965 (Box 1)
    - Abrams, M., 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - Baldwin, Hanson W., 1945-1963 (Box 1)
    - Baring, Walter S., 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Bible, Alan, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Caccia, Harold, 1950-1966 (Box 1)
    - Cannon, Howard W., 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Churchill, Winston, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Clarke, Brig. Gen. Bruce C., 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - Conant, James B., 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - Crosby, Bing, 1944 (Box 1)
    - A-C, miscellaneous, 1928-1965 (Box 1)
    - Dager, Brig. Gen. Holmes E., 1944-1961 (Box 1)
    - Douglas, Justice William O., 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - Drake, Brig. Gen. Charles C., 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1950-1965 (Box 1)
    - Figl, Leopold, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
    - Fulbright, Sen. J. William, 1943-1963 (Box 1)
    - D-F, miscellaneous, 1928-1965 (Box 1)
    - Gray, Brig. Gen. Hobart R., 1945-1960 (Box 1)
    - G-H, miscellaneous, 1939-1966 (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1960 (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Robert W., 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Robert F., 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - I-K, miscellaneous, 1938-1966 (Box 1)
    - LeMay, Gen. Curtis E., 1959 (Box 1)
    - Liddell-Hart, B. H., 1930-1965 (Box 1)
    - McClellan, Sen. John L., 1950-1962 (Box 2)
    - Moseley, Gen. George Van Horn, 1938-1960 (Box 2)
    - Murphy, James L., 1950-1966 (Box 2)
    - L-N, miscellaneous, 1945-1967 (Box 2)
    - Pace, Frank, Jr., 1950-1965 (Box 2)
    - Passanante, Anthony J., 1956-1960 (Box 2)
    - Patton, Gen. George S., 1943-1958 (Box 2)
    - Plimpton, Francis T. P., 1963 (Box 2)
    - Rhee, Syngman, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Rivers, L. Mendel, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Rolvaag, Gov. Karl F., 1963 (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Mrs. Franklin D.), 1956 (Box 2)
    - Russell, Gov, Charles H., 1958 (Box 2)
    - O-R, miscellaneous, 1945-1963 (Box 2)
    - Settle, Vice Adm. T. G. W., 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Smith, DeWitt C., 1960-1967 (Box 2)
    - S, miscellaneous, 1924-1965 (Box 2)
    - Taft, Sen. Robert A., 1951 (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Gen. Maxwell D., 1945-1964 (Box 2)
    - United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - Van Fleet, Gen. James A., 1951-1959 (Box 2)
    - Vanderbilt, Cornelius Jr., 1960 (Box 2)
    - T-V, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Ward, Maj. Gen. Orlando, 1945-1951 (Box 2)
    - Wood, Ray, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    - Young, Sen. Stephen M., 1965 (Box 2)
    - W-Y, miscellaneous, 1945-1961 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, 1945-1965 (Box 2)
  - Outgoing
    - Miscellaneous, 1935-1944; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1945-1966; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Of others
    - Wood, Abigail (Mrs. John S.), 1965-1967 (Box 3)
- Writings
  - About John S. Wood
    - By Hanson W. Baldwin, reproduction (Box 3)
    - By various writers, 1967 (Box 3)
  - By John S. Wood
    - Articles
      - The American fighting man [MISSING: folder empty, 7/14/2017], 1960; reproduction (Box 3)
      - Artillery notes from foreign journals, in Artillery Journal, 1935; printed material (Box 3)
      - Artillery strengths in the French offensives of 1918, in Field Artillery Journal, 1934; printed material (Box 3)
      - Counterbattery in war of movement, in Field Artillery Journal, printed material (Box 3)
      - Courage conquers, original typescript (Box 3)
      - Czech outlook seen as dark, in Des Moines Register, 30 Mar 1938; printed material (Box 4)
      - The disarmament dream, original typescript (Box 4)
      - The German military doctrine, in Field Artillery Journal, 1934; printed article, English and Spanish versions (Box 4)
      - The Italian artillery in Ethiopia, in Field Artillery Journal, 1936; 1937; printed material; includes clipping in Italian (Box 4)
      - The liaison problem, in Field Artillery Journal, 1935; printed material (Box 4)
      - Notes on disarmament and the United States, typescript (Box 4)
      - Notes on foreign armies, in Field Artillery Journal, printed material (Box 4)
      - Notes on military measure for United States security, typescript and mimeographed copies (Box 4)
      - Notes on war of movement, circa 1935; printed material (Box 4)
      - The officer's code of honor, typescript (Box 4)
      - Prophet or fantasy, in Field Artillery Journal, circa 1934; printed material (Box 4)
      - Promotion, 1937; printed material (Box 4)
      - Reorganization, in Reserve Officer, 1936; reproduction of typescript; printed material (Box 4)
    - Autobiography, Things remembered and things considered, typescript with handwritten corrections and research notes
    - Christmas greetings, 1962-1965; printed material (Box 4)
    - Column, "Notes and comments," in Field Artillery Journal, 1937-1939; printed material (Box 4)
    - Foreword to research study on 4th Armored Division during 1944 campaign, 1950; carbon copy of typescript; correspondence; includes report (Box 4)
    - Interview (radio), 1952; mimeographed copy (Box 4)
    - Memoranda on World War II artillery, 1939-1946; typescript (Box 4)
    - Notes and outlines, 1949-1961; holograph; typescript; mimeographed copies (Box 4)
    - Obituaries for friends, 1957-1963; typescript; printed material (Box 4)
    - Obituary for himself, by Wood, typescript (Box 4)
    - Speeches, 1945-1966; holograph; typescript (Box 4)
    - Telephone conversation transcript, typescript (Box 4)
- Photographs
  See also Memorabilia: Albums, below.
  - Austria, primarily Vienna and Salzburg, includes some postcards (Box 5)
  - Camps, maneuvers, parades (Box 5)
  - England, France, during World War II, circa 1942 (Box 5)
  - Friends, 1957-1960 (Box 5)
  - O'Donnell, Emmett, General, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Patton, George S., Lieutenant Colonel (Box 5)
  - Patton, George S., General, circa 1942 (Box 5)
  - Pre-World War II (Box 5)
  - Scott, Charles L., Major General, circa 1945 (Box 5)
  - Self with others, 1937-1945; 1952-1966; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Stillwell, Joseph, General (Box 5)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1937-1945 (Box 5)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1952-1966 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Album, 1938-1951; photographs (Box 4)
  - Album, Vienna, 1948-1953; photographs (Box 6)
  - Address books, lists of addresses, 1952; 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - Awards, citations, degrees (Box 6)
  - Biographical material, manuscript, news clippings, 1939-1965 (Box 6)
  - Biographical material volume, Abiding Heroes, obituaries, memorials, tributes (Box 6)
  - Book lists (Box 6)
  - “By Deeds Alone” The Official March of the 4th Armored Division, audiorecording; wood_js_002; 1 VinylDisc (Box 6)
    Track list: 1. By Deeds Alone; 2. Men of Honor; 3. Hit the Leather (Official March of the 2nd Cavalry Regiment); 4. Armored Guard Mount Medley - Yellow Ribbon, Gary Owen [Garryowen], STRAC Armor, The Girl I left Behind
  - Commission, Captain in Coast Artillery Corps, 1917
  - Date books, 1947-1966; 22 volumes; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Financial records (Box 8)
  - 4th Armored Division, 1944-1961 (Box 8)
  - International Refugee Organization, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Maps, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
  - Military Pay and Retirement Bill, 1959-1963; printed material (Box 8)
  - Programs and events attended, 1947; printed material (Box 8)
  - Schweizerischer Tennisverband / Association Suisse de Tennis Offizielles Jahrbuch / Annuaire officiel, 1963; 1965 (Box 8)
  - Training manuals, 1945-1951; printed material; mimeographed copies (Box 8)
  - U. S. Army releases, 1945-1946; mimeographed (Box 8)
  - United States Information Service, Vienna, Austria, 1950-1951; bulletins (Box 8)
  - Historical and Pictorial Review, 37th Armored Regiment (4th Armored Division), 1942 (Box 8)
  - Historical and Pictorial Review, 22 Armored Field Artillery, 66th Armored Field Artillery, 94th Field Artillery (Box 8)
  - Historical and Pictorial Review, Division Headquarters Company, Combat Commands A and B, Division service Company, 144th Signal Company, Headquarters Division Trains, 24th Armored Engineer Battalion, 84th Armored Reconnaissance Battalion, 704th Tank Destroyer Battalion (4th Armored Division), 1942 (Box 9)
  - The German Artillery in the Breakthrough Battles of the World War, by Col. George H. Bruchmuller (Box 9)
  - Fourth Armored Division Convention, wood_js_001; audiorecording; John Shirley Wood, speaker; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)